A Guide to the United Daughters of the Confederacy, Dr. Harvy Black Chapter Records, 1862-2010
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
United Daughters of the Confederacy, Dr. Harvy Black Chapter Records, 1862-2010
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1990-050
4.4 cu. ft. 8 containers
Records of Dr. Harvy Black Chapter, United Daughters of the Confederacy. Contains files devoted to local Confederate veterans, as well as chapter financial records, minute books, membership records, printed materials and scrapbooks.
United Daughters of the Confederacy. Dr. Harvy Black Chapter (Blacksburg, Va.).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The United Daughters of the Confederacy, Dr. Harvy Black Chapter Records were deposited with Special Collections in 1990, with the exception of the scrapbooks and the Elisha Epperson letters, which were deposited in 1991. Additional minute books, scrapbooks, membership applications, and chapter correspondence and business records were donated in 2010, after the chapter disbanded. More materials were received in 2013 and 2017.
Biographical/Historical Information
The United Daughters of the Confederacy was established in Nashville, Tennessee in 1894. Comprised of female descendants of Confederate Civil War veterans, the organization was formed to preserve materials and places significant to Confederate history and to provide assistance to needy families of Confederate veterans. The Blacksburg, Virginia chapter, named in honor of local resident and Fourth Virginia Infantry surgeon Harvy Black, was formed in 1896. The chapter disbanded in 2009.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains the records of the Dr. Harvy Black Chapter of the United Daughters of the Confederacy (UDC). Apart from the chapter's records, the collection also contains files devoted to local Confederate veterans--most noteworthy of which are the letters of Elisha Epperson (67th Virginia Infantry). Among the official chapter records are financial records, minute books, and membership applications. The collection also contains a small set of printed materials, including convention programs and proceedings, booklets, and newspaper clippings. A group of scrapbooks completes the collection.
Arrangement
The collection is divided among the following series:
I. Confederate Veterans, 1862-1967. This series includes a set of letters written from Giles County, Virginia by Elisha Epperson (67th Virginia Infantry) to his wife (accompanied by portraits of the Eppersons). The series also contains a set of local applications for Southern Crosses of Honor, many of which were completed and signed by the veterans themselves. Also found here are biographical data on local veterans and information on local World War I and II soldiers who descended from Confederate veterans. This series is arranged by material type.
II. Chapter Financial Records, 1896-1982. In addition to two early treasurer's books, this series also contains the chapter's membership tax lists and a file on the local Confederate Memorial Fund. This series is arranged by material type.
III. Chapter Minutes, 1896-2009. This series contains a set of books detailing the proceedings of the chapter's meetings and is arranged chronologically.
IV. Chapter Membership Records, 1896-1981. This series contains applications for membership in the Dr. Harvy Black chapter. The membership forms include information on the applicants, their family, and their ancestors' roles in the Civil War. The series also contains a small set of forms for members who transferred from other chapters. The series is arranged by document type, then alphabetically.
V. Printed Materials, 1897-1999. The Printed Materials Series contains both UDC and non-UDC publications. It includes a set of the Dr. Harvy Black chapter's yearbooks, as well as programs and proceedings for national and state UDC conventions. Among the non-UDC publications are several booklets devoted to various aspects of Civil War history. The newspaper clippings in this series contain information on UDC activities as well as historical topics, including articles on ex-Confederate immigrants to South America.
VI. General Materials, 1896-2009. Comprised of a wide variety of materials, this series includes such materials as correspondence, the chapter's charter, photos of Blacksburg's Smithfield Plantation, and a commemorative ribbon from the 1905 Confederate veterans' reunion in Christiansburg, Virginia. A 1994 oral history interview with Bernice Willard is also included.
VII. Scrapbooks, 1935-2005. The scrapbooks in this series contain such items as programs, essays and newspaper clippings on the United Daughters of the Confederacy and on Civil War history.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Transfers
The following items were transferred to the Rare Book Collection:
The Capture of a Locomotive: A Brilliant Exploit of the War. Atlanta, GA: Franklin Printing, 1895.
Craig's Share in the War Between the States, 1861-1865: A Historical Sketch.[New Castle, VA: Craig Chapter, United Daughters of the Confederacy, c. 1912].
Custodians of Imperishable Glory.[Atlanta, GA: Stone Mountain Confederate Monumental Association, 1925?]
Hale, Gertrude Henkle. Mary Custis Lee.[Richmond, VA?: Virginia Division, United Daughters of the Confederacy, 1936].
The History of the Home for Needy Confederate Women, 1900-1904. Richmond, VA: J. L. Hill, 1904?].
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
United Daughters of the Confederacy. Dr. Harvy Black Chapter (Blacksburg, Va.).
Subjects:
Blacksburg (Va.); Civil War; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.); United States--History--Civil War,1861-1865
Contents List
- SERIES I. CONFEDERATE VETERANS, 1862-1967
  - Elisha Epperson letters, 1862-1864 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Southern Cross of Honor applications, 1905-1920
    - A-K (Box-folder 1-2)
    - L-Z (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Biographical data on local veterans, 1916-1967, n.d. (Box-folder 1-4)
  - Records of World War veteran descendants of Confederate veterans, 1945-1946, n.d. (Box-folder 1-5)
- SERIES II. CHAPTER FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1896-1982
  - Treasurer books, 1896-1922, [2 items] (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Chapter membership tax lists ("per-capita blanks")
    - 1951-1963 (Box-folder 1-7)
    - 1964-1972 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Financial Documents, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Financial Correspondence, 2009-2010 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- SERIES III. CHAPTER MINUTE BOOKS, 1896-2009
  - Minute books
    - 1896-1902 (Box-folder 2-1)
    - 1920-1935 (Box-folder 2-2)
    - 1936-1953 (Box-folder 2-3)
    - 1953-1965 (Box-folder 2-4)
    - 1966-1986 (Box-folder 2-5)
    - 1986-2005 (Box-folder 6-1)
    - 1999-2009 (Box-folder 6-2)
    - 2000-2003 (Box-folder 6-3)
    - 2005-2009 (Box-folder 6-4)
- SERIES IV. MEMBERSHIP RECORDS, 1896-1981
  - Membership applications, 1896-1981
    - A-C (Box-folder 3-1)
    - D-G (Box-folder 3-2)
    - H-L (Box-folder 3-3)
    - M-O (Box-folder 3-4)
    - P-S (Box-folder 3-5)
    - T-Z (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Membership transfer forms, 1921-1975 (Box-folder 3-7)
- SERIES V. PRINTED MATERIALS, 1897-1999
  - Chapter yearbooks, 1947-1968, [4 items] (Box-folder 3-8)
  - Convention programs, 1899-1980, [4 items] (Box-folder 3-9)
  - Convention proceedings, 1897-1903, [5 items] (Box-folder 3-10)
  - Booklets, 1904-1958 (Box-folder 3-11)
    - "Constitution and By-laws of the United Daughters of the Confederacy," n.d.
    - "The First White House of the Confederacy, at Montgomery, Alabama," 1951
    - Huse, Caleb, "The Supplies for the Confederate Army: How They were Obtained in Europe and How Paid for," 1904
    - "Montgomery, Alabama: Cradle of the Confederacy," n.d.
    - Morgan, W. H. "Southern Cross of Honor," 1913
    - Rutherford, Mildred Lewis. "What the South May Claim; or, Where the South Leads," 1916?
    - Smith, Essie Wade Butler, "Forty Years with the Virginia Division, United Daughters of the Confederacy," 1946?
    - Gielow, Martha S. "To the United Daughters of the Confederacy, Replying to Mrs. Lizzie George Henderson's Letter," 1906?
    - "Unveiling of the Bust of Thomas Jonathan Jackson, 'Stonewall,'" 1958
    - "Virginia Leads," 1916
  - Newspaper clippings, 1926-1999, n.d. (Box-folder 3-12)
- SERIES VI. GENERAL MATERIALS, 1896-2009
  - Correspondence, ephemera and photos, 1896-1980, n.d. (Box-folder 3-13)
    Scope and Contents note
    [See also Oversize Materials]
  - Chapter History Documents, 1954-1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Oral history interview with Bernice Willard [audiocassette], 1994 (Box-folder 3-14)
  - Cemetery and monument materials, 1991-2006, n.d. (Box-folder 6-5)
  - Correspondence, programs, and chapter history, 2006-2009, n.d. (Box-folder 6-6)
  - Letter of disbandment, 2009 (Box-folder 6-7)
- SERIES VII. SCRAPBOOKS, 1935-2005
  - Scrapbooks, 1935-2005
    - 1935-1946 (Box-folder 4-1)
    - 1946-1949, n.d. (Box-folder 4-2)
    - 1953-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 5-1)
    - 1967-1968, n.d. (Box-folder 5-2)
    - 1970-1975, n.d. (Box-folder 5-3)
    - 1975-1988 (Box-folder 5-4)
    - 1995-2002 (Box 7)
    - 2002-2005 (Box 7)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS, 1897
  - Certificate of chapter organization, 1897